Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
Frederick William MacMonnies papers
1874-1997
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
MacMonnies, Frederick William
7.0 linear feet
The papers of sculptor Frederick William MacMonnies date from 1874 to 1997 and measure 7.0 linear feet. Found within the papers are biographical material, a diary, correspondence, personal business records, project files, two sketchbooks and sketches, writings, printed material, and photographs. Well over one-half of the collection consists of Mary Smart's research files for her biography of MacMonnies, A Flight with Fame, as well as clippings regarding her research and a copy of the book.
Provenance
The bulk of Frederick William MacMonnies papers were donated by the artist's granddaughters Louise Wysong Rice and Marjorie Vander Velde in 1988 and 1998. Some, but not all, of the papers were originally loaned for microfilming and were later included in the donations. A small addition to the papers was transferred from the Smithsonian's Museum of American Art Library in 1981.
Separated Material
In 1965, five scrapbooks were loaned by Marjorie Vander Velde for microfilming on reel 245, and returned. In 1984, Louise Wysong Rice loaned letters from Augustus Saint-Gaudens to MacMonnies for microfilming on reel 3042. These materials are not described in the container listing of this finding aid.
Related Material
Also found in the Archives of American Art are four letters from MacMonnies to Allan Marquand cataloged separately, and a typescript "The Form of the Princeton Monument" lent by Elric Endersby in 1976 and microfilmed on reel 1094.
Alternative Forms Available
Portions of the collection are also available on 35 mm microfilm reels 3042 at Archives of American Art offices, and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of the collection as described in this finding aid may not reflect the exact order of the collection on microfilm.
Restrictions on Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment.
Biographical Note
Frederick William MacMonnies (1863-1937) of New York City, was a well known sculptor of the Beaux-Arts School, equally successful in France as in the United States. He was also a highly accomplished painter and portraitist.
Frederick William MacMonnies was born on September 28, 1863 in Brooklyn Heights, New York, the son of Juliana Eudora West and William MacMonnies. From an early age, MacMonnies showed skill in fashioning figures from wax. Because the Civil War put an end to his father's prosperous importing business, MacMonnies had to leave school at a young age in order to earn money to support the family.
With the help of a stone carver friend of his father, MacMonnies became a studio assistant to Augustus Stint-Gaudens in 1880. MacMonnies also studied at night at Cooper Union. In 1882 Saint-Gaudens promoted MacMonnies to apprentice and encouraged his development as an artist. MacMonnies began studying drawing at the National Academy of Design and occasionally attended classes at the Art Students League. It was during this time that he became better acquainted with Saint-Gaudens' important patrons and colleagues including John LaFarge, Charles F. McKim, Stanford White.
In 1884 MacMonnies left for Paris to study first at the Académie Colarossi and later at the É Ecole des Beaux-Arts under Jean Alexandre Falguière. In 1888 he opened a studio in Paris where he mentored artists including Janet Scudder and Mary Foote. He married a fellow artist, Mary Louise Fairchild in 1888. They had two daughters, Berthe Hélène and Marjorie. They were divorced in 1909, and Mary married painter Will Hicok Low later that year. MacMonnies married his former student Alice Jones in 1910.
MacMonnies executed commissions for Stanford White and John La Farge. In 1889, he won a competition to complete a statue of Nathan Hale for City Hall Park. He won a medal in the Paris Salon for his statue of Hale and a second medal for his statue of James T. Stranahan, earning status as a master artist. In 1891, he was commissioned to produce the central fountain for the World's Columbian Exposition in Chicago.
Even though MacMonnies travelled annually to the United States, he maintained his primary residences and studios in Paris and Giverny, France. He was also an occasional painter and had a solo exhibition at the Durand-Ruel Galleries in the United States in 1903. In 1905 his Bacchante and Infant Faun statue became the center of controversy when it was rejected by conservative groups in Boston. It was later acquired by the Metropolitan Museum in New York City. In 1915 he returned permanently to the United States.
MacMonnies was an Academician of the National Academy of Design, Chevalier of the Legion of Honor of France and hors concours at the Paris Salon allowing him to submit works directly to the Salon without initial scrutiny by judges.
Frederick William MacMonnies died of pneumonia on March 22, 1937 in New York City.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of sculptor Frederick William MacMonnies date from 1874 to 1997 and measure 7.0 linear feet. Found within the papers are biographical material, a diary, correspondence, personal business records, project files, two sketchbooks and sketches, writings, printed material, and photographs. Well over one-half of the collection consists of Mary Smart's research files for her biography of MacMonnies, A Flight with Fame, as well as clippings regarding her research and a copy of the book.
Biographical material consists of a student card to the É Ecole des Beaux-Arts, a certificate of registration as an American Citizen, the wills of MacMonnies and his second wife, Alice, and a biographical note by Alice MacMonnies.
The most significant item in the collection is MacMonnies' diary that documents his first voyage to Europe where he was anxious to pursue his studies in sculpture. His well-described activities during his first year of study in Paris, Munich, and in Italy illustrate the excitement and challenges faced by serious art students in the mid-1880s.
Correspondence includes letters exchanged between MacMonnies and colleagues including George Grey Barnard, Paul Bion, and John Flanagan. There are also letters from MacMonnies to his second wife Alice and to his daughters, Berthe Helene (Betty) and Marjorie MacMonnies.
Personal business records include deeds for land in Long Island, New York, certificates of copyright for MacMonnies' art work, and a rental agreement for and inventory of MacMonnies' studio in Giverny, France.
Project files are found for the Fountain Barge of State at World's Columbian Exposition in Chicago and other sculpture pieces. There is also a sheet of preliminary sketches for the statue General George B. McClellan.
Art work consists of two sketchbooks, drawings, and plaster casts of sketches for planned sculpture projects for the New York Public Library, a memorial statue for Edwin Booth, and a drinking fountain.
Writings include a manuscript by MacMonnies concerning the adverse effects modernity was having on beauty in art, a typescript concerning George Grey Barnard's statue of Lincoln, and memoirs by Mary Fairchild MacMonnies Low in which she describes her early life, her first encounter with MacMonnies, and their life together in Paris and Giverny, including a visit from Stanford White and his wife.
Well over one-half of the collection consists of Mary Smart's research files for her biography of MacMonnies, A Flight with Fame. Printed material includes clippings and a copy of Mary Smart's book.
Photographs are of Frederick MacMonnies, family members, his studio, a horse used as a model for The Horse Tamers, and art work.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged as 10 series:
Series 1: Biographical Material, 1884-1921 (Box 1; 5 folders)
Series 2: Diary, 1884-1885 (Box 9; 1 folder)
Series 3: Correspondence, 1880-1971 (Box 1; 0.6 linear feet)
Series 4: Personal Business Records, 1874-1931 (Box 1; 6 folders)
Series 5: Project Files, 1891-1935 (Box 1, 9-10; 27 folders)
Series 6: Art Work, 1910-1914 (Box 1, 8-9; 1.1 linear feet)
Series 7: Writings, 1912-1917 (Box 2; 12 folders)
Series 8: Mary Smart's Research Files, 1908-1997 (Box 2-6, 9; 4.2 linear feet)
Series 9: Printed Material, 1896-1996 (Box 6-7; 13 folders)
Series 10: Photographs, 1889-1911 (Box 7, 9; 8 folders)
Names and Subject Terms
This collection is indexed in the online catalog of the Archives of American Art under the following terms:
Subjects:
Booth, Edwin, 1833-1893; McClellan, George Brinton, 1826-1885; White, Stanford, 1853-1906; Ecole nationale supérieure des beaux-arts (France)--Students; World's Columbian Exposition (1893:--Chicago, Ill.)
Subjects-Topical:
Sculptors--New York (State)--New York
Types of Materials:
Diaries; Manuscripts; Memoirs; Photographs; Sketchbooks; Sketches; Typescripts
Names:
Barnard, George Grey, 1863-1938; Bion, Paul; Flanagan, John F., 1865-1952; MacMonnies, Alice; MacMonnies, Betty; MacMonnies, Berthe; MacMonnies, Marjorie; MacMonnies, Mary Fairchild, 1858-1946; Smart, Mary, 1917-
Series Descriptions/Container Listing
- Biographical Material, 1886-1921, Series 1:; (Box 1; 5 folders)
  Biographical material consists of a student card to the Ecole des Beaux-Arts, a certificate of registration as an American Citizen, the wills of MacMonnies and his second wife, Alice, and a biographical note by Alice MacMonnies.
  - É Ecole des Beaux-Arts Student Card, 1886 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Certificate of Registration of American Citizen, 1913 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Frederick William MacMonnies' Will, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Alice MacMonnies' Will, 1915 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Biographical Notes by Alice MacMonnies, 1921 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Diary, 1884-1885, Series 2:; (Box 9; 1 folder)
  MacMonnies' diary describes his first sailing to Europe, daily activities during his first year of study in Paris and Munich, and descriptions of travel in Italy.
  - Diary, 1884-1885 (Box 9, Folder 1)
- Correspondence, 1880-1971, Series 3:; (Box 1; 0.6 linear feet)
  Correspondence includes letters exchanged between MacMonnies and colleagues including George Grey Barnard, Paul Bion, and John Flanagan. There is one letter each from Daniel Chester French, Archer M. Huntington, Charles F. McKim, and Frances Davis Millet. There are also letters from MacMonnies to his second wife Alice and to his daughters, Berthe Hélène (Betty) and Marjorie MacMonnies. There are scattered letters from Helen Gordon Glenn, Rita Lydig, and a telegram to Alice from General John J. Pershing, a former suitor.
  - Correspondence, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Letters to Helen Gordon Glenn, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1884 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1890-1894 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 1895 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1896, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
  - Correspondence, 1897, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
  - Correspondence, 1898 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1900-1901 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1903 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1904-1910 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1911 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 1912-1913 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 1914, (5 folders) (Box 1, Folder 22-26)
  - Correspondence, 1915, (10 folders) (Box 1, Folder 27-36)
  - Correspondence, 1916, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 37-39)
  - Correspondence, 1917, (5 folders) (Box 1, Folder 40-44)
  - Correspondence, 1918 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Correspondence, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Correspondence, 1921-1924 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Correspondence, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Correspondence, 1926, (3 folders) (Box 1, Folder 49-51)
  - Correspondence, 1927, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 52-53)
  - Correspondence, 1928-1929 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Correspondence, 1930-1932 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Correspondence, 1933-1934 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Correspondence, 1935-1936 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - Correspondence, 1937 (Box 1, Folder 58)
  - Correspondence, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 59)
  - Correspondence, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 60)
  - Correspondence, 1940-1971 (Box 1, Folder 61)
  - Letters from MacMonnies to his Daughters, 1908-1932, (12 folders) (Box 1, Folder 62-73)
  - Letters from Mary Fairchild MacMonnies Low, 1900-1940 (Box 1, Folder 74)
  - Letters to and from Will Hicok Low, 1880-1928, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 75-76)
  - Letters from Maggie MacMonnies Courant and Juliette Courant, 1910-1921, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 77-78)
- Personal Business Records, 1874-1931, Series 4:; (Box 1; 6 folders)
  Personal business records include deeds for land in Long Island, New York, certificates of copyright for MacMonnies' art work, a rental agreement for and inventory of MacMonnies' studio in Giverny, France, and miscellaneous receipts.
  - Deeds for Land, 1874-1890 (Box 1, Folder 79)
  - Copyright Certificates, 1895-1896, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 80-81)
  - Rental Agreement for Property in Giverny, 1914 (Box 1, Folder 82)
  - Inventory of Contents of MacMonnie's House in Giverny, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 83)
  - Miscellaneous Receipts, 1914-1931 (Box 1, Folder 84)
- Project Files, 1891-1935, Series 5:; (Box 1, 9-10; 27 folders)
  Project files for the Fountain Barge of State at World's Columbian Exposition in Chicago, the Princeton Battle Monument, the Marne Battle Memorial, and statues General George B. McClellan, and Civic Virtue contain letters, photographs, and printed material including clippings, brochures, blue prints, and a book The Princeton Battle Monument. There is also a sheet of preliminary sketches for the statue General George B. McClellan.
  - Fountain Barge of State at World's Columbian Exposition in Chicago, 1891-1935, (5 folders; oversized Material Housed in Box 9) (Box 1, Folder 85-89)
  - Statue General George B. McClellan, 1903-1907, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 90-91)
  - Princeton Battle Monument, 1908-1927, (10 folders) (Box 1, Folder 92-101)
  - Statue Civic Virtue, 1914-1935, (5 folders) (Box 1, Folder 102-106)
  - Marne Battle Memorial, 1929-1935, (5 folders; oversized Material Housed in OV 10) (Box 1, Folder 107-111)
  - Two Oversized Photographs of the Fountain Barge of State at World's Columbian Exposition in Chicago, 1893, (from Box 1, Folder 88) (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Three Oversized Blueprints for the Marne Battle Memorial, 1928, (from Box 1, Folder 109) (Box OV 10)
- Art Work, 1910-1914, Series 6:; (Box 1, 8-9; 1.1 linear feet)
  Artwork consists of two sketchbooks and sketches for planned sculpture projects Beauty and Wisdom for the New York Public Library, Edith Gould with Goat, Hamlet for Edwin Booth memorial, and a Utica, New York drinking fountain.
  - Sketchbook 1, undated, (2 folders) (Box 1, Folder 112-113)
  - Sketches, undated, (Oversized Material Housed in Box 9) (Box 1, Folder 114)
  - Plaster Casts of Sketches for Planned Sculpture Projects, 1910-1914, undated (Box 8)
  - Oversized Sketchbook 2, undated (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Oversized Sketch, undated, (from Box 1, Folder 113) (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Writings, 1912-1917, Series 7:; (Box 2; 12 folders)
  Writings consist of a manuscript by MacMonnies concerning the adverse effects modernity was having on beauty in art, a typescript concerning George Grey Barnard's statue of Lincoln, family anecdotes by Berthe Hélène MacMonnies, reminiscences by René de Quélin who also apprenticed in Saint-Gaudens' studio, dietary advice for Mrs. MacMonnies, and miscellaneous poetry. Of special interest are Mary Fairchild MacMonnies Low's memoirs in which she describes her early life, her first encounter with MacMonnies, and their life together in Paris and Giverny, including a visit from Stanford White and his wife.
  - Manuscript Concerning the Loss of Beauty in Art through Modernity by Frederick MacMonnies, 1912 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Typescript Concerning George Grey Barnard's Statue of Lincoln, 1917 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Memoirs by Mary Fairchild MacMonnies Low, undated, (6 folders) (Box 2, Folder 3-8)
  - Family Anecdotes by Berthe Hélène MacMonnies, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Autobiographical Account by René de Quélin, undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Dietary Advice for Mrs. MacMonnies, 1913 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Miscellaneous Poetry, undated (Box 2, Folder 12)
- Mary Smart's Research Files, 1908-1997, Series 8:; (Box 2-6, 9; 4.2 linear feet)
  This series consists of research notes compiled by Mary Smart for her biography of MacMonnies A Flight with Fame, including photocopies of letters, notes, typescripts, clippings, miscellaneous printed material and scattered photographs copied from published sources or taken by Smart of art works and locations from MacMonnies' life. The Mary Foote file and the Stanford White file contain photocopies of letters from MacMonnies. The Will Hicok Low file contains photocopies of letters dated 1885-1903 from Augustus Saint-Gaudens.
  - American Academy and Institute of Arts and Letters, 1976-1977 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Angels, 1969 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Archives of American Art Correspondence, 1979-1997, (10 folders) (Box 2, Folder 15-24)
  - Atlanta, undated (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Atlantic Crossings, undated (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Bacchante and Infant Faun, 1980-1997, (7 folders) (Box 2, Folder 27-33)
  - George Grey Barnard, undated (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Paul Bartlett, undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Beaux Arts, undated (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Cecilia Beaux, 1995 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Eugène Berteaux, undated (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Paul Bion,undated, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 39-40)
  - Edwin Booth, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Bronxville, 1990 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Brooklyn Things, 1970-1993, (4 folders) (Box 2, Folder 43-46)
  - John Mason Brown, 1937-1970 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Butler Family, 1970 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Henry White Cannon, 1968-1969 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Chicago Fair (World's Columbian Exposition), 1971-1976, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 50-52)
  - Civic Virtue, 1966-1987, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 53-55)
  - Denver, 1975, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 56-57)
  - René de Quélin, undated (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Thomas Wilmer Dewing, undated (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Diana, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - William de Leftwich Dodge, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 61-62)
  - Emmet Family, 1968-1982, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 63-65)
  - Book The Epicurian, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Faun with Heron, 1976-1995, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 67-68)
  - Finances, 1971 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - James Wall Finn, 1970-1994, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 70-72)
  - Mary Foote, undated, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 73-74)
  - Daniel Chester French, 1975-1992, (2 folders) (Box 2, Folder 75-76)
  - Alfred-Jean Garnier, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Charles Dana Gibson, undated (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - Giverny, 1968-1992, (3 folders) (Box 2, Folder 79-81)
  - Giverny, 1968-1992, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 1-3)
  - Helen Gordon Glenn, 1976-1988, (7 folders) (Box 3, Folder 4-10)
  - Gramercy Park, 1966 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Karl Gruppe, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Nathan Hale, 1969-1977, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 13-15)
  - Hallowell Painting, 1976-1994 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Thomas Hastings, 1935 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - History of Sculpture and Art, 1969-1995, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 18-20)
  - The Horse Tamers, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Evelyn West Hughan, 1969, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 22-23)
  - Indianapolis I, 1908-1995 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Indianapolis II, 1969-1979 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Jones Family, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Gozo Kawamura, undated (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Elijah R. Kennedy, undated (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Thomas Lamont, 1990-1994 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Library of Congress Doors, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Charles Lindbergh, 1972-1978 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - DeWitt M. Lockman 1927 Interview of MacMonnies (Annotated Photocopies), undated, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 32-34)
  - Mary Fairchild MacMonnies Low, 1970-1990, (9 folders) (Box 3, Folder 35-43)
  - Will Hicok Low, undated, (4 folders) (Box 3, Folder 44-47)
  - Will Hicok Low and Julienne Low, 1971, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 48-49)
  - Rita Lydig, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 50-51)
  - MacMonnies' Ancestors, 1969-1990 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - MacMonnies' Childhood, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - MacMonnies' Descendants, 1971, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 54-56)
  - MacMonnies' Obituaries, 1971 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - MacMonnies' Grave, 1967-1969 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Notes Concerning MacMonnies' Letters to his Daughters, undated, (8 folders) (Box 3, Folder 59-66)
  - Notes Concerning MacMonnies' Letters to his Daughters, undated, (4 folders) (Box 4, Folder 1-4)
  - MacMonnies Typescript "The Beautiful Arts of Painting and Sculpture" (Annotated Photocopy), undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Berthe Hélène MacMonnies, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Frank MacMonnies and his Granddaughter Joan Huber, 1970-1995, (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 7-8)
  - Maggie MacMonnies and Juliette Courant, 1969, (3 folders) (Box 4, Folder 9-11)
  - Marne Battle Memorial, 1962-1989, (3 folders) (Box 4, Folder 12-14)
  - Marne Battle Memorial Rededication as Statue of Fraternity, 1987-1989, (4 folders) (Box 4, Folder 15-18)
  - General George B. McClellan, undated, (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 19-20)
  - Charles F. McKim, undated, (3 folders) (Box 4, Folder 21-23)
  - Models, undated (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Claude Monet, 1978-1995, (Oversized Material Housed in Box 9) (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - New York Distinguished Visitors' Medal, 1970-1972 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - New York Public Library Fountains, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Herman Niemeier, undated (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Paintings, 1983, (4 folders) (Box 4, Folder 29-32)
  - Courtlandt and May Palmer, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Pan of Rohallion, 1935-1974, (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 34-35)
  - Paris, 1974 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Pax Victrix, undated (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Miss Pelzer, 1970 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Perseus and Andromeda, undated (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Victor Peter, undated (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Peters Family, undated (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Poetry, undated (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Princeton Battle Monument, 1972-1984, (7 folders) (Box 4, Folder 43-49)
  - Prison Ship Martyr's Monument, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  - Edmondo Quattrocchi, 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  - Auguste Rodin, 1970-1981 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  - Theodore Roosevelt, undated (Box 4, Folder 53)
  - John H. Roudebush, undated (Box 4, Folder 54)
  - Augustus Saint-Gaudens, 1971-1990, (8 folders) (Box 4, Folder 55-62)
  - Salons, undated (Box 4, Folder 63)
  - John Singer Sargent, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 64)
  - Janet Scudder, 1971, (3 folders) (Box 4, Folder 65-67)
  - Sculpture - Early, undated (Box 4, Folder 68)
  - Sculpture Honor and Awards, 1970-1992, (6 folders) (Box 4, Folder 69-74)
  - Sculptures - Medallions, 1969-1972, (3 folders) (Box 4, Folder 75-77)
  - Sculpture - Not Done, 1948 (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - Sculpture - Other, 1971 (Box 4, Folder 79)
  - Sculpture - Portraits (Busts, Statues, and Reliefs), 1958-1988, (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 80-81)
  - Sculpture - Statuettes, 1976-1986 (Box 4, Folder 82)
  - Shakespeare, 1993 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Jacob H. Shiff, undated (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Henry Warner Slocum, undated (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Societies, undated (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Frank Squier, undated (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - James S. T. Stranahan,undated (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Lorado Taft, undated (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Myron C. Taylor, 1954-1993 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Mary Laurence Tonetti, 1975-1977, (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 9-10)
  - Utica Fountain, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Sir Henry Vane, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Venus and Adonis, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Versailles, undated (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Washington Arch, undated, (3 folders) (Box 5, Folder 15-17)
  - Benjamin West, undated (Box 5, Folder 18)